Oh, Johnny and Jorge when um James Brown
is going to be uh sharing some slides,
too.
>> Okay,
>> let's see.
Yep. Do you see him? And we can give him
privileges.
>> All right, cool. And looks like we are
letting everybody in. Um
and this will just need a moment. We
will get the meeting started here.
>> All right. Cool. I think Okay. Yeah.
Everybody who was in the lobby is in
now.
>> All right. Great. Thanks, Johnny. Hello
everyone. Uh my name is Jorge Gonzalez
uh uh medical psilocybin program manager
for the department of health. Welcome to
the end of life care committee with uh
Dr. Larry Leman uh and who will be
facilitating the meeting today along
with a presenter and we'll get to that
in just a moment. But as a reminder,
just want you to know that this meeting
is going is being recorded and will be
available uh on our website soon uh
after that, you know, several days. And
so remember to keep all language
appropriate uh because this will be uh
out for the public. Uh and also that is
the other one of the reasons why we do
have cameras off for folks except for
the department of health staff and
presenters. Uh so that you know uh
sometimes uh you know things may be in
the background and we want to keep
limit. And so with that uh we'll have uh
Larry Leman uh take the meeting. Thank
you Larry.
>> Great. Thanks Ry. Well welcome
everybody. Good to see you at least here
all of you. Um, so I just want to give a
little update of where where we're at
with the the meetings. So each meeting
we've been choosing like a different uh
topic to um to focus on. Today we're
going to focus on the criteria for end
of life care and maybe criteria that may
or may not be appropriate and and
priorities for the equity health fund.
Um James Brown is kind enough. He's a
our farm D uh psychedelic pharmacist. I
don't know if he likes that name, but
I'll giving him that name. He's um going
to talk some about things that come up
with end of life care, multi-organ
system failure, and psilocybin. So,
we're going to start with that um with
the more of the longer range picture. on
um July 10th, we're going to have at
least one uh speaker joining us, Mary
Kosamano, who's was a therapist at the
John's Hopkins End of Life Studies. And
um not confirmed yet, but hopefully
somebody from the NYU end of life
studies just to share what they've
learned from um from doing those. And as
we as we move kind of into late summer
and fall, I I kind of hope we can kind
of bring everything together for all
these different meetings and start
writing up, sharing guidelines. um we
haven't really wanted to be the first
out of the gate for those because a lot
of what we're doing requires integrating
with the rest of it but I think we're
getting to the point where we can start
putting more of our ideas out to to the
you know the whole advisory board and
other people.
So having said all that um want to
invite James to to uh to talk um on the
pharmacy at end of life care and so
happen
>> James I've enabled you to mic
>> and also James you are a presenter but I
can run the slides for you and
>> is that okay Jorge can you run those for
me? I'd really appreciate that.
>> I sure will appreciate you.
>> And you can also turn on your camera as
well if you'd like.
There we go. And again, Larry, uh, thank
you for allowing me to present this
information and the Department of Health
as well. Thank you so much for allowing
me to present this today.
>> Did you get that slide deck, Jorge, that
I sent earlier today? Uh uh is this is
the the end of life committee scopes and
responsibilities. Is this the the orange
and blue?
>> Yeah, those are my slides, not James's.
>> Okay, let me look uh at my inbox. I've
been in backtoback meetings. So, let me
see if that is available. James,
>> sure. If not, I can try to share here
and try to do it.
I'm just an amateur, but I'll I can try
see. All right, give me a one second.
Ah,
I do see that.
Okay, give me one second and I will open
that.
>> Thank you.
>> Yes.
All right, there you are, James.
>> Thank you so much.
>> You're welcome.
>> Okay, everybody. Uh, James Brown. I'm a
farm D from New Mexico. Um today, um I
do represent an organization called Five
Degrees North Healing Foundation, which
is a nonprofit here in New Mexico that's
focused with veterans, first responders,
and again PTSD patients in the future,
and we're hoping to be able to provide
those services in the future. So, thank
you, Jorge. Next slide, please.
So what I want to do is everybody knows
you know a a good high level here um I
just broke it down and did some I really
like uh visuals and so how does
psilocybin work in the brain everybody
knows it's you know it's a prod drug and
once it's converted to solosin of course
everybody knows that 5HT2 receptor u
there's the normal state you know that
we like to do so what does it do you
know it activates that serotonin
receptors it temporarily you know quits
the DMN zone right that's something
that's very important in research and
that's out there with that we need to
kind of focus in on and in my
presentation some talks about that today
it's the brain's habits or autopilot
system as you guys know um increases
communication between u the regions the
different the two regions there the
different hemispheres uh again what
happens next with psilocybin patterns
loose and networks become more flexible
and connected um which is very important
right because that helps with your
experience um that also helps with alter
perceptions
uh new perspective as insights uh
greater mental flexibility um and that
also helps with increased connected
brain regions again and that DMN zone
that default mode network is very
important so what's your takeaways from
this slide psilocybin temporarily shifts
the brain out of a rapid pattern and
into a more open connected and adaptable
state next slide Okay.
You know, and in my background, we do a
lot of drug drug interactions or what we
call pharmaccoinetics and
pharmacodnamics.
And I think that that's important here.
Um, I'm just going to present some of
that. Um, because those things are are
mechanisms that can overlap with each
other. Uh, these interactions are
necessary. One substance affects um
another by competing at the receptor
site. um sometimes are synergistic and
sometimes they're not. The two substance
work together more strongly if it's
synergistic synergistic and then they
also can be adaptive and one substance
can enhance the effects of another. Um
and then with pharmacocinetics drug drug
interactions what happens is you have
that metabolism or transport of the
substance can be changed. For instance,
if somebody has liver disease or has
liver um cancer or issues with their
liver, um again you would see those
biomarkers, but as you look for that
patient, you'll see those enzymes,
right? Those CYP450s are very important
with this. Um and again, you can also
incre increase or decrease the blood
concentration of the of these
medications. Uh next slide, Jorge.
Again, just a little bit more about drug
drug interactions as we get in here. Um
the big thing to take away with this
again is that for instance blood
thinners likely don't affect the
metabolism of psilocybin but as an
individual patient who likely who is on
blood thinners which we could come
across um if they have a history of
cardiovascular disease or a history of
clotting um they also might have a
history with arhythmias. And so that's
something just to think about um with
those different disease states that we
get down into this presentation shortly
here with um it's important to take away
those different disease states with this
end of life type of focus. Um next slide
please.
So what happens in the elderly? I think
that's a big takeaway. you know, talking
to Larry, I think one of the big focuses
is is with our group, what happens in
the elderly. And I'm going to explain
some of those things here shortly about
what people's kinetics and dynamics
change um in the in their state um as
they become um more elderly or more
frail or other things that can develop
with their different uh body dynamics.
Aging affects the kinetics of the body
by altering your absorption, your
distribution, metabolism, and excretion.
These kinetic changes will lead to a
important here slow elimination and
increased sensitivity to certain
medications. So sometimes what that
means is um they're not going to if
you're orally eating something and you
orally intake something um that can be
affected by those different uh kinetic
pieces as you age. Next slide please.
Here we go. This is what this is kind of
a breadandbut slide here. kinetics
changes in the elderly. So what's going
on? The liver reduces P450 enzymes,
right? So that's a slower metabolism.
What happens with the brain? It has
reduced volume and cognition. Renal
function changes. It's reduced number of
kidney nephrolysis, nephrons, sorry.
Reduce filtration. That's the big thing.
Ability and function. So again, you
know, so you're going to, you're going
to produce less renal, less clearance
that way. Um, and that can affect
somebody's hydration status.
Cardiovascular system. What happens
there? reduce cardiac output um and
again increased stiffening of the
arteries. So again you have that
happening muscular skeletal what happens
there loss of muscle mass and strength
and again what happens with respiratory
uh reduced lung capacity and increased
gas exchanges that can help with your O2
CO2 issues with that and some other
things and digestive I think that's
important because psilocybin and sloin
do affect the digestive tract um and
reduced liver function is very big in
there and reduced um your GI motility
slows down and you have like most
elderly they get constipation and
there's some references there for you
guys. Uh next slide.
So what I did was I put this um into
more of a visual because I like visuals
and so again um heart and blood vessels,
what's going on there? Um you have your
body composition, increased body fat.
Okay, well that's that's important. And
again you you have loss of mass, right?
Which affects your creatinin levels. Um
and then you have reduced kidney volume.
You have again some numbers happening
with those nefrons reduction there. And
then your GFR as everybody knows it your
your goal filtration rate that decreases
and can be affected. But your brain in
the elderly I think that's a good focus
here with this slide. Um, I really think
that as we think about Parkinson's and
we think about Alzheimer's and we think
about these different brain things that
as you get older happen to us, you know,
you do lose volume um in your brain. Um,
you also it also affects your ability to
um the amaloid plaque, right? That's a
big thing that we like to talk about.
Um, that can be constantly affected
there. Formation happens at a greater
pace and you can't clear it. Um and
again you know digestive system you know
again I think you know again within
psilocybin it does affect the digestive
system and there's a lot of serotonin
receptors in the digestive tract you
know um majority of your serotonin
receptors are actually found in your
digestive tract um if if you guys wanted
to know that about 80% um versus 20%.
Okay so um next slide please.
So what does that mean and how will it
affect my patients? How does it affect
me? That's important to me, right? So
let's say somebody's on uh benzoazipene,
something that's very common, maybe
dasopam, clinazopam, these are a little
bit more long acting, but you do see
these in the elderly. Um and you have a
metabolite that's also through the
CYP450 enzymes. Um and that that
metabolism again is slowed as you get
older and this translate into even a
longer half-life in these patients. So
that that's important right because then
if somebody's having these effects you
can get the falls you can get increased
drowsiness. Okay. So what happens with
psilosin psilocybin they have an active
metabolite right that also is reduced
and that conversion is reduced in the
elderly. You need to know that as a as a
clinician, as a takeaway, as a as a
facilitator, you know, as we sit here
and and and learn more and more daily um
that keeps coming out, some of the
things that we need to know is that, you
know, your metabolism slows as you age,
and that translates into a longer
half-life with medications, which also
can increase to increased
hallucinations. um I don't want to
they're they're more of like um effects
of the of the psilocybin itself but
those hallucinations can increase in
length of your session and so just be
aware of that you know dosing would be
affected at that point so just be
advised uh an individual's patients age
will be an important role with their
metabolism of psilocybin the response
will impact both their physiological and
their psychological aspect of their
experience understanding age related
differences is will enable the
facilitator and also the clinicians the
ability to tailor dosing strategies. I
love that. Individualize please. Next
slide.
Practical applications. Facilitators and
also clinicians should have access to
the client's overall medical history.
That's important. You guys know that
this group is very talented and very
smart. uh adjust the individual dose for
your patients known to their disease
condition changes. If they have a liver
health problem, start with a lower dose
to avoid prolonged and intensified
hallucinogen effects or other effects.
Monitor the patient closely for delayed
reactions and during and after the
administration session. So you you might
want to have to tailor a little bit more
time and effort and also just the way
you talk to them and the way you present
this to them as a therapy will be
different uh based off of that liver
health history. Uh patients taking
medication metabolism that's metabolized
by the liver antidopressants and
convulsants others may experience these
type of drug drug interactions
metabolism with psilocybin. Now it's
very low but there is some history and
research is coming out more and more
about this. Next slide.
GI history and health is important. We
also want to look at their weight and
composition. Right? We talked earlier
about their decreased muscle mass. Uh
for example, if a patient has a higher
BMI or a higher body mass versus a lower
BMI, they often experience doses of
psilocybin to achieve the same level. So
what happens is they require a larger
dose if they have a higher BMI.
Typically, if they have a lower BMI,
like a maybe a female or or an
individual frail patient, uh you know,
sometimes they typically think about
that would have a lower dose um and it
can decrease that um effectiveness or
increase their effectiveness based off
that BMI. Just awareness. Again, I just
like to point these things out. Examples
of lean body mass would be patients like
bodybuilders or patients who um have a
quicker rate. Um, and so what happens
with them is a higher rate of metabolism
will occur will lead to a quicker onset.
That's important. Like so if you're
going to metabolism at a faster rate,
you're going to experience those things
right away. Your peak onset's going to
come up and then you're going to you
might do that um at a very fast rate,
right? And those are people who um
particular are athletes or couch
potatoes is in there. Hydration is
important. We've talked about that in
some of the subcommittees. Adequate
hydration is very important while you do
these sessions. prior is very important
um because the blade onset can have a
heightened effect. Next slide.
GLP1s. This is something I talked to
Larry about. I think this is a hot
topic. Um I wanted to bring this in
because I think it's I think it's
important as a medication interaction.
People are on GLP1s. You'll you'll be
surprised to find out who was on them.
Um if a patient's taking GLP1s, the
patient can experience a delayed onset
because remember it slows down GI
motility. So if you are taking an oral
substance and and you're slowing down
that metabolism, right? Those four
things that we talked about before, the
absorption, your metabolism, and then
that effect is going to be delayed.
Okay? And that's important to know. So
what what happens with this? We're okay.
We can deal with this, right? As
clinicians and and and as as providers
and facilitators, that's okay. If
they're on GOPs, no problem. Um just
know about this. the delayed gastric
absorption can be delayed up to two to
six hours depending on the patient's
previous GLP dose and the GLP medication
itself. There are a lot different out
there. There's a lot of things out there
that are different. Peptides included.
Uh please keep that in mind. And the
patients individual kinetics and
dynamics again like we've talked about.
Combinations of psilocybin solosin with
GLP1s can cause an increase in
occurrence of nausea and vomiting. So
these meds already cause nausea and
vomiting. GMP1's number one side effect
is nausea and vomiting. So are a lot of
other meds but FYI if you if you give
psilocybin which is known some for most
people to cause nausea and vomiting you
have an increase in this and so both of
these agents can cause an increase in
the individual and it's something to be
aware of during your session. Next
slide.
And if anybody wants to know about GLP1s
real quick, I would give them about
sevenday wash out period uh prior to
their their their psilocybin experience,
their session, their journey. Um prior
se 7-day wash prior to that would be a
good GLP1 wash out period. Uh okay, drug
drug interact. There are several ways
psilocybin and salosin medications can
interact with each other. Again, that's
a the blood thinner example I gave
earlier. Uh Jorge, next slide, please.
Another
one here is is is comes up a lot and I'm
sure you guys will experience it if if
not I'm sure it has is SSRIs and SNRIs
is very common. So again this is this is
literature this is research out there
and it's awareness sometimes this will
cause a blunting effect I keep telling
people I keep saying that in these
meetings blunting effect is very
important to be aware of that blunting
effect can cause the solosin or
psilocybin not to work and you don't get
that experience or that journey or that
container change that you're needing and
so just be aware of that that things
like fluoxitine
is an SSRI which can lead to longer time
of complete elimination from the
So what happens is fuxine uses uh six
it's very long halflife and so if you're
going to wash out somebody if you're
going to give somebody a holiday um it
it'll it'll take a long time and so you
might not want to do that but again
that's individualized I just want to
give you guys an example of of some of
these drugs that might need to be
individualized and looked at when you're
going through these reviews another one
is wellbutrin this is a very common
medication for uh that you'll see out
therap has a very long halflife and they
call it a dinar. It's a basically helps
with um again depression other things
and it help inhibiting the re-uptake of
both norep and dopamine. So two
different mechanism pathways there which
can have more cascading effects. So it's
not just those uh bupropriion psilocybin
have different mechanisms of actions and
com directly compete so that and they
don't directly compete at the receptor
therefore they're unlikely to have an
interaction effect. So things like SSRIs
would but things like the dinars won't.
So uh duoxitine is a very common one.
This is a SNRI that does have an
interaction. So those things might take
up to two weeks for a wash out. They
might not take any depending on your
patient and your experience and your
comfortability as a facilitator and as a
clinician. Next slide. There's a couple
more examples here real quick. uh
mortazzipene that's very common for
sleep in the elderly that blocks 5HT2A
receptor um is predicted to cause a
blunting effect again that's a more
blunting maybe two week out two week
wash maybe even a little less but uh
martaspine does have a long halflife
things like trazadone a lot of people
are on that that are elderly use that
for sleep again blocks 5HT receptor at
low doses and blocks serotonin reuptake
pump at higher doses maybe this is like
a fiveday wash if you need to again wash
it all Next slide. There's other type of
drug interactions that I want to let you
guys know about. Stimulants, opioids,
alcohol, and other things that are
enhanced hallucinations like marijuana.
Uh, next, please.
Serotonin syndrome. What is that, James?
That's something I just wanted to be.
It's very rare. You should hopefully
never see this, but we if we do, it's
something serious. Um, again, usually
encountered with polyarm pharmacy. So
somebody comes to see you is not
completely being honest or is very
heightened on other substances
uh both elicit and non-elicit depends on
what it is those things can have effect
on their experience and you need to know
that okay a rare condition called excess
serotonin activity uh and it's used with
medications things like mais which a lot
of people are not on highdose SSRIs or
things that have other type of snri high
dose these are things that you need to
be aware of psilocybin alone. Again, if
you're taking just psilocybin or solosin
alone, it is very very rare and very low
risk. Um what to watch for if you do
have somebody who does experience a
serotonin syndrome, um agitation,
confusion, sweating, heart rate, rapid
heart rate, uh tremors, muscle
twitching, um healthy individuals not on
any type of medications are again very
unlikely. Next slide, Jorge.
And we only have a few more slides left.
We're almost done.
Something I wanted to bring up was
HPPPD. What is that? That's hallucinag
hallucinogen persisting perception
disorder. Again, these are things that
are very rare, but you need to know that
does happen, right? If an elderly
patient has an liver issue, and again,
we talked about increased hallucination
effects or increased length of time of
that hallucination experience. Um, HPV
might be one of those. So that could
also be construed as more of a long
acting a very rare thing that it's a
very persisting
uh psychological psilocy psychedelic
experience. Uh visual trails light
sensitivity uh mild visual distortions
they occur at a very low percentage. Uh
and what happens is they're very likely
though to be with high repeating doses
poly substance again and underlining
mental health conditions. So something
there. Bottom line, healthy individuals
with perception and controlled use.
Again, very uncommon to have HPPPD. Next
slide.
Again, this is about just the management
of serotonin. If you're if you're
experiencing that, um what do you do? Um
discontinuation again, sedation, uh
benzoazipines, things like Adaban help
to reverse that as well as HPPPD. So
both serotonin syndrome and HPPPD of
course is uh benzo is first line. So
they're going to throw that on and it
basically competes at the receptor and
occupies that receptor at a higher
affinity than psilocybin and it starts
competing and now your body starts to
you you'll have that reverse effect.
Things that a lot of people don't know
about is the administration of a
serotonin antagonist. Oo love this.
That's cyproepadine. We have that in the
hospitals. And so if that was something
that you experienced as a clinician
hospital, that's an option. So again,
there's some dosings there. Love to talk
to you about it if you have questions
about that. Uh next slide, please.
And then uh last and uh foremost is this
Parkinson's part. I just wanted to spend
a minute on Parkinson's and other type
of conditions that we're going to see in
the elderly. And it's something to think
about with Alzheimer's, Parkinson's,
very common early results of of the
recent trials. Again, these are very
recent trials and studies are showing
psilocybin when combined with
psychotherapy
if it's well to if it's well tolerated
and there is a potential benefit for
treating both motor and non-mo symptoms
of PD. I think that's huge. I think as
we get into this and somebody could do
some research, Larry, that'd be
something amazing to do. I'm not sure if
you can. I know you're busy, sir. But,
you know, something like this needs to
be done because there's some positive
results out there showing improvement in
mood, improvement in cognition,
improvement in their motor functions.
That's an improvement in quality of
life, right, for these people. That's
what that means. That means that they're
going to have a better life. And so,
that's important to think about and
important to do research on. There is
some negative results, severe anxiety,
um, that can be managed with different
meds. and also maybe dosing was in
there. Um, and increased risk for again
those salute snagging effects. Um,
that's it everybody. Um, I just wanted
to take some questions now or Larry,
it's up to you now to to to moderate.
I'm I'm done. Thank you so much. But I'm
here as questions come up.
>> Yeah, thanks James. I think that was a
great talk and just as you're giving
that I'm just thinking like the
different ways that all this applies.
you know, we've talked about having to
get information out to, you know,
prescribers, you know, around the state.
So, seems super helpful there to people
may be referring to the program as well
as for the facilitators and licensed
licensed providers. Um James, I will say
we actually do have a study that um it's
not looking at the effect of psilocyb
related psychedelic. Um it's not
directly on the effect on Parkinson's,
but it's people who have Parkinson's
cancer other things. And we're looking
at um how does that affect their
adjustment to having Parkinson's. So we
do have one Parkinson studies at UNM. So
thanks for that shout out. Um I think
it'd be great James to take questions
now. um you're getting a lot of you know
uh thumbs up parts and all. I agree. I
think it was a great presentation and um
I think we should just drop right into
questions on your presentation.
>> Sounds great.
>> All right. And uh let's see. Um, and as
a reminder, yeah, if you want to ask a
question, you can raise your hand um on
Teams with the icon that says raise with
a hand up on the top banner. Um, and
first we've got Lita Fati. And Lita, um,
let's see, your mic is enabled and you
can unmute.
>> Thank you so much, James. That was
fantastic. Thank you. Thank you. Thank
you. And it's such a special population,
both the elderly and also those who have
a terminal diagnosis. And I was con uh
wondering if you know of any studies
where um you've seen interactions with
psilocybin and um lactulose or refaxamin
you know we have a very large um
population of patients with endstage
liver disease in our state unfortunately
due to alcohol use disorder and I want
to you know just you know wondering if
you've seen any um in that space any
studies or experience
um in that space.
>> Dr. Fatimi, uh amazing question. I think
this is a very very important thing to
bring up because people do have this uh
ammonia issues a lot in this population
and currently there's nothing in the
space that I've seen um itself actually
study the laculos or refaxamine like you
were saying in the chat. Um, I think
it's something that as a as a clinician,
as somebody, you know, when you're doing
your med reviews, it's something to
know. Um, this will be a binder. And so,
I think a lot of what we see is the way
to this works, right, is how do we get
rid of these ammonia levels is basically
is it binds it up right in the gut. And
so, I think if when you're taking the
solosin or psilocybin, you're going to
you're going to see that binding as
well. And so I think you just when
you're if you see somebody with
refaxamin or with lactulose it's
something to think about their dosing
and absorption as well. um you might not
get a dose at all to them just reading
that out right doc to yeah maybe maybe
delayed right if it if it does show up
then you get maybe like a dumping
>> right
>> so it's something if they can discontin
>> um I would definitely you know advise on
that prior to it's a very half the half
flight's very quick on those it only
take a couple days
>> which is also dangerous right because
you know you were talking about a group
of patients who have um a cerosis
induced encphylopathy. And so that's
what we use these medications for. And
so if we you know stop it and they don't
get rid of the pneumonia that's built
up, then they start having
hallucinations and they have enslopathy.
So it's a very delicate balance in that
patient population. And so yeah, thank
you for that. Um
>> no, it's a great question. I'm glad you
brought that up. It's something we need
to
>> Yeah. Thank you. Thank you. And then you
know have you seen a lot of studies you
know recently I've been looking more at
um um dementia you know of different
varieties and looking at the
effectiveness of psilocybin
specifically as an anti-inflammatory
agent um in that population which you
know we see a lot of inflammation in the
brains of individuals with uh
Alzheimer's dementia and I'm just you
know haven't I don't know if you know of
any other studies that you see that in
where you know we know that psilocybin
modulates the uh immune system and
different IIL's
um but I'm just curious to pick your
brain about
>> I like it um I have three studies um
once I I can share this with you I'll
email you my presentation there's three
studies that I did find the reduction in
neuroinflammation
it does show some some promising effect
with that
>> you know neuroinflammation reduction
thus promoting neuroplasticity Right. So
the more neuroplasticity we can get, the
better outcome. Right. And I think it
does show that Doc that we're getting
that reduction in inflammation.
>> Thank you so much. Thank you. This was
fantastic. Appreciate you, James.
>> No, appreciate you.
>> All right, let's see. And next we've got
Gregory Evans. And Gregory, uh, let's
see, your mic is enabled and you can
unmute.
>> Good work, James. That was beautiful.
Um, for all the nerds,
um, it's a lot of stuff that I think a
lot of people aren't really thinking
about. I wanted to touch on a couple
things, but first in response to Dr.
Fatmi's last statement around
inflammation. Um although salosin is
does have an anti- an inflammation
anti-inflammatory effect um it's
important to try to track um the
presence ofenosine
in different species and cultigens.
um that it will um increase the efficacy
like it's a synergistic effect of
anti-inflammatory behavior and I think
it's something that is just beginning to
be studied. Um, I probably could pull up
a couple papers on on the subject for
you, but I think that's a very
interesting thing to watch, especially
in aging populations.
Um, on the
BMI,
I wanted to bring up just to kind of
circle back on that to
um
just kind of rein restate that like
solosin is not lipophilic. So it there
like BMI doesn't necessarily have the
like an effect on dosage but what it
does similar to the conversation about
renal issues is that you it may be an
indicator that something else is
happening in the gut. So if somebody is
um you know exercising a lot and has a
excellent BMI, they probably have a
solid gut health. And so I I just want
to caution and I don't think that like
necessarily the the presentation
suggested that people dose based on BMI,
but I just wanted to reinforce and maybe
get you to speak a little bit more on um
what the BMI can be an indicator of and
what actual dosing measures should be
paid attention to, if that makes sense.
>> Gregory does actually. So on that slide,
um my big takeaway for everybody was
really just thinking about as they get
elderly, right? These elderly patients
typically lose their body mass. You
know, they're not they're not doing
activity levels, they're not doing
things that would help to rebuild that
muscle. Uh they don't go and and they're
very their activity is very limited.
Their walking ability is very limited.
And so with this loss of of muscle mass,
um, and so that was kind of the takeaway
was really is as you lose mass, whether
you're a female or a male, it could be
different rates of course that people
that lose this. Um, if you're females,
you know, you'll see them as frail and
little and and sometimes males, you see
that too towards the end. Um, and so
it's just something just that when
you're sitting on something like this
and you're having your patient and
you're going over their meds and you're
going over their, you know, their body
chemistry and you're going over their
their their their
disease states, right? And you're saying
this elderly, frail person who's really
at, you know, maybe 80 pound and wet,
um, you know, we call it, right, in the
weight world, right? You know, they're
80.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I'm 120. Just want to
say like with that conversion, you know,
these people are not going to require a
dose as as high of a dose. So you might
be like, man, I'm thinking I I somebody
needs like a 20. Well, they might not
even need a 20. They might need
something like a lower. They might need
15.
>> It's just something that individualize,
tailor that, Gregory, you know, I mean,
tailor that thought to like that
patient's body mass. If they're a couch
potato, let's say that you you'll get
those, right? We get those two people
too on hospice. So we get that on this
end of life type of spectrum who are
morbidly obese and their BMI is at 50
60%. And and then you and then you're
like what kind of dose are they going to
need? And that's kind of was that slide
to really just start thinking about.
>> Oh yeah,
>> because pharmacologically. So question
about that like so so where the 5HT2A
receptor density baseline expression is
what's what's going to affect the uh the
efficacy of the dose. Right? So,
whatever potency per gram or whatever
goes into a body, um, you could have a
200lb person with a high density of HT2A
expression will have a a stronger
reaction than 130 lb person with a low
expression. What is what in in aging
populations are we tracking um
basically just receptor density? Is
there a test? Is there a way we can test
for that density as a baseline
um in in our like intake?
>> Great question. I don't think there's
currently an ability or a way to test
that at a cost-effective
patient per patient rate. You know what
I mean? Like I but there's something out
there with that. Yes. But I don't think
it's something that you as a clinician
could could do effectively or cost
effectively
>> at this point in time. But it's a great
question. Um, I think Dr. Fatame has a
response. I also saw that Larry may have
wanted to say something.
>> Thank you so much for the discussion,
Mike. Oh, so sorry.
>> No, I'm just saying I I don't want to
say I don't want to say anything. I I
want to listen to you.
>> Well, I want to listen to you, too,
Larry.
>> I want to listen to Larry, too.
>> Right.
Um I actually was going Thank you for
that uh comment Gregory. Um, one of the
things that came up in our session when
we were doing in our academy, we had a
pharmacist out of Colorado and she
presented on, you know, all these cases
that she has worked in, you know,
regarding psilocybin ceremonies that
she's been preparing patients for over
800 patients that she had um, you know,
helped um, either reduce medications or,
you know, guide and in how-tos or you
know, stopped patients from going into
ceremony because there were just on too
many things. But one of the things that
she was discussing was um you know the
concern that for you know serotonin
syndrome we don't really see it but she
said that in patients where they were
concerned about serotonin syndrome were
those who had taken too much zopran
and I never would have thought of that
but you know especially in the end of
life patient community zopran is you
part of the comfort kit. And so I'm just
bringing that up as a like a caveat of
us like paying attention to those
medications that do modulate serotonin.
Um and Zopran if they've taken you know
many doses in in like a 24 48 hour
period then it's something that we need
to pay attention to so that we prevent
uh complications from happening. Um and
James I don't know if in your research
and studies you know you saw anything
like that you this was more of an
experiential
that she was um she was sharing with us
you know but that's a pretty big number
of patients 800 is pretty good number I
would say per for any research study and
that's that's where she had seen the
complications but I didn't look it up to
see if anything's been published about
it. I don't know if um anybody in the
group has seen it.
>> Um Dr. I haven't seen the specific
zopran in the literature but I know that
you know of course with highdose zopran
uh you know we get that QT prolongation
and you do get some type of uh cardiac
um issues and so people who are can have
that u you know very common if sopran um
with with this type of medication as
well can cause QT prolongation
um and so I think you would see that
effect coming across as a concern
>> right thank Thank you.
>> All right. And looks like Ian Dunn
has got his hand up and your mic is
enabled.
Good afternoon everyone. Hi, my name is
Ian Dunn. Uh I am the chair of the
medical psilocybin advisory board. I did
not get to introduce myself earlier so
so sorry about that. Uh thank you James
for your presentation. I just wanted to
also um lean in with Dr. fati that uh
zopran I have seen it cause um serotonin
syndrome in patients when they were
taking mushrooms. Um correct me if I'm
wrong any of the pharmacists in the chat
you know a lot more than I do but um I
believe it's because it knocks off the
serotonin syndrome from the G or the
serotonin from the GI um leading to
there being extra serotonin. I could be
completely off base. Um, I've heard this
was about two years ago when I had this
explained to me. Um, but yeah, no, that
is definitely a problem. And then on
board with um what Gregory and James
were saying earlier about the weight, I
know weight isn't the best metric to
use, but it is one of the more
affordable metrics to use in this
program. Um, and while I don't think it
should be the only deciding factor,
right, we shouldn't just say, "Oh, well,
you weigh you get x number of milligrams
per kilogram." I do think um like
especially in the end of life scenario
when patients get smaller, they
typically have less blood volume and
therefore a higher concentrate of active
drug in their bloodstream um when it's
all said and done. So, we have to be
extra careful with them. Um so I do
think it's important to note it never
not necessarily be the entire um
decision center but yeah sorry that was
a lot of information but basically I
agree with um James and Gregory that um
weight is important and also Dr. Fatami
that um Zopran
occasionally can cause some serotonin
syndrome issues.
I have a couple this is Larry a couple
of comments from the research um
research world. Um we actually you know
most of the studies do actually allow
zopran to be given to people that um are
using psilocybin. I my understanding is
the concern is more of the polyfarm
pharmacy that if it's zopran and another
serotonin drug whether it's an
anti-depressant or such an psilocybin
that's at least more of the you know
more of the concern than necessarily
simply a dose of of zopran and just to
give a little bit of a um different
point of view on the weight like the
studies that were initially done um were
using like weight-based dosing and they
actually found it wasn't that relevant
And so, at least in the research world,
nobody's using weight- based dosing
anymore. It's just using a a set dose
because I think as I think it was Ian
said, there's a lot of other factors
that get involved. What is people's
experience, other things on the on the
metabolism, but you know, I guess I
would encourage not focusing that much
on weight.
>> You're right, sir. The the big thing
about the serotonin and the research uh
with the negative outcomes or negative
effects is with that poly pharmacy when
they're on multiple SSRIs are on
multiple types of things that are
hitting the serotonin the vertazzipene
SSRI high dose then they're on high dose
uh odansron higher than 16 milligrams
you know if they've received a dose
that's higher than 16 over a you know
24-hour period you know those are things
to start thinking about and so I'm 100%
with you Larry and group I think it's
the polyfarm pharmacy we we do see that
effect come up a you know, could come up
and you could see that.
>> Well, James, I want to thank you again.
This is like really an awesome talk and
it'd be good to have it, you know, have
it up on the website for people and and
as we start thinking about outreach to
um, you know, outreach to clinicians and
facilitators. Um, you know, I think the
information in your talk is really key.
And you know, we've talked about having,
you know, 20 hours more for end of life
care. And so I think this, you know, is
a lot of the pharmacy component that
could be included in that. So I really
thank you for sharing it all, James.
>> Thank you, sir. I appreciate you and
thank you for letting me present today.
>> And um Jorge or Johnny, if you can um
throw my slides up there, I can
transition into those.
>> All right. I sure will. Dr. in.
There you are.
Great. Thanks. Um, so I just want to
start a little bit just to kind of put
us in this perspective of where we are
are at with the end of life committee.
Like these are the scopes that we
started with. um you know I guess it's
been about five months ago and um the
ones that are um started here are ones
that um are relevant somewhat to today's
talk but we've actually kind of covered
most of these uh uh most of these over
over the time. So that's why I was
mentioning I think we're getting to the
point where we can start writing out our
suggested guidelines. Um but today we
will look at the definition and the
scope for end of life uh uh care. So
next slide.
Um and again you know we talked early on
that um end of life therapy could be
viewed from different lenses you know
palative of hospice care um and that we
supported the idea of expansive time
frames including from the time of
diagnosis and um also that the idea that
recognized end of life um can be due to
the natural aging process. So just as a
reminder to to us that was some of our
our early perspectives. Next slide.
Um you know we talked earlier again this
is again something from previous time
that eligibility can include individuals
across a range of end of life
experiences including those diagnosed
with a terminal illness including people
who may have months or years remaining
those living with serious or lifeling
conditions. those approaching imminent
transition and that our our model our
goal was to recognize that end of life
is not a single moment and that we're
not you know focusing on end of life is
uh simply meaning hospice care.
Next slide.
And so um I I wrote out these slides.
I've shared that with, you know, some
people on the, you know, on the
committee. But, um, I really just put
these up because I was just going to do
an open-ended discussion, but I thought,
well, let me just take a stab at, you
know, writing some potential, um,
guidelines. And, um, so that's what
that's what these are here. They're
really, um, just as a touchstone to
start having discussions. So, one idea
would be to include progressive illness
with estimated lifespan under three
years. any diagnosis of cancer with the
exception of skin cancer except for
melanoma natural end of life anticipated
within two years and the partner family
caretaker of a person participating in
end of life psilocybin therapy those are
you know four areas I think that um one
can certainly view different um uh
different time spans as being
appropriate and maybe add different ones
but I wanted to put these out and I
think the other thing when we put these
out is I want to put that there's the
what's eligibility and what is priority
especially when we look at the equity
fund. Next slide.
Um so one question would be like
prioritization guidelines and I know the
equity committee in desert has been
looking at those and have looked very
carefully at the socioeconomic criteria
and I think you know we want to be
consistent with that with end of end of
life care. Um but we do have some things
that are a different perspective and
whether we should be prioritizing end of
life within a year within six months um
you know for the equity fund. My thought
would be that that those priorities are
within the construct of the people
already meet the socioeconomic criteria.
Um but it may be a reason because I
imagine once we get going $600,000 isn't
going to last that long and you know
folks who are um co approaching end of
life could reasonably be argued to be a
priority rather than waiting quote for
the next year of the fund.
And the last slide um is you know that
we're talking about inclusions but I
think that as we've gone through like
different areas we've had talks like
today um you know all the studies that
are out there all the states that are
out there you know you know have a lot
of various exclusions and I think we
have to look at those and see how
appropriate they are for you know for
end of life. I mean if um um like in in
general I can you know people are you
know not not to be using marijuana not
to be uh you know drinking alcohol
within a day or two but you know some of
those may not really be relevant if
we're doing end of life care especially
as people approach the the hospice time.
So substance use um you know although
have certain concerns I think one could
argue to be relaxing those concerns at
end of life. Um similar with mental
health. I mean there's things that are
generally felt to be contraindications
um such as bipolar borderline
personality. But um again those um first
of all I mean honestly those are not all
that evidence-based. They've been sort
of selected early on in a lot of the
trials and continue that in each of the
states. But um when you're in facing end
of life and such it may be reasonable to
relax those and not consider certain
things contraindications
even uncontrolled hypertension or
diabetes or you know forms of heart
disease. Um again this needs careful you
know consideration but um it seems like
one could argue at end of life to to
relax some of those criteria from a from
a compassion compassionate point of
view. We certainly don't want somebody
who has um lifespan of six months to be
trying to get their sugar in their
hemoglobin A1C in better control so they
can uh be doing psilocybin. So I think
we have to look at it a little bit in
that context. Similarly the endorgan
damage um you know the perspective that
James shared here I think is is a good
one. If someone has endstage liver
disease, we don't want to disqualify
them as we would in certain studies, but
we may want to decrease the dose and
understand that the lifespan may be
wronger.
Even suicidal wishes and suicidal wishes
becomes a you know it's a different
perspective and when you're looking at
some when someone who has an expected
lifespan of six nine months all of a
sudden you're you know I mean the
questions that we even ask people on the
screening do you wish you were dead you
know do you have any plans there's a
different perspective and so again it
just seems like we may not want to be
ruling people out um from end of life
use of psilocybin for some of the same
suicidality that we we might in somebody
in different conditions. So again, um
all of these are kind of slides just
kind of created for just discussion
points to start, you know, looking about
how we're going to do that. So I just
threw that up there. Um really like to
hear, you know, public comment and the
committee about, you know, how we can
adjust these as we start um start making
our our guidelines and our
recommendations.
open to open to thoughts and comments.
>> All right, let's see. Looks like first
we've got um JS
um and I have allowed your mic and you
can unmute when you're ready.
And to unmute um there is an icon at the
top banner that says mic. Yeah, there
you go.
>> Hey guys, it's Jeff. It's
Sorry, I had you on my laptop and on my
cell phone because I'm sitting in a
coffee shop. Can you hear me? Okay.
>> Yes.
>> Okay, cool. I just turn one off and I
need muted this one. All right. Hey, so
first of all, it is just always so
inspiring to be with you guys. I just
want to say that at the outset. I'm just
it's just incredible the work you're
doing and and the just experience and
knowledge you put into it. It's
inspiring. I do have a few questions,
Larry. Just a little bit of feedback. um
questions really on the equity fund,
you know, um rather than um limit it to
to you know, certain levels of end of
life, maybe the better way to do it is
just is just, you know, thinking in
terms of the equity fund, how maybe and
maybe this will end up being a bad idea,
but maybe a portion of the equity fund
to different uses so that it's available
for
different types of people in different
situations be them substance abuse, end
of life, uh you know, depressive
disorder, so that one bucket maybe
doesn't end up using all the resources
rather than say within a particular um
qualified condition. There's a
subriteria within that condition that we
qualify. I might just suggest that that
we, you know, we're creating a an
incomebased financial criteria that
maybe that would just be the standard
for anybody who qualifies in this space
because certainly somebody who may be
three years out may have just as much
distress as somebody a year out. I think
that's you know just just a thought and
I I think maybe you know it might be
good for just the whole everybody in the
advisory board to think about maybe how
we
aortion it for different uses rather
than those kind of subriteria within
each use. Just a thought. And then um on
the the issue of family members or
caretakers of people in end of life
situations, did I understand your
recommendation, Larry, that it would be
a that a family member or caretaker
could also qualify for psilocybin
therapy, but only if the person that
they were looking after was also engaged
in that therapy.
>> Jeeoff. Yeah, thank you. And by the way,
I want to make sure everyone knows uh
Senator Steinborn was a a lead advocate
and creator of the bill bill. So Jeff,
we love having you on these calls. So
thank you so much. Um that's what I
wrote up there. You know, I you know, I
I think part of um you know, part of
this is that trying to figure out what
was what was the spirit of doing this.
One could argue, you know, that anyone
who is dealing with grief of a of a
family member, regardless who that was,
is appropriate. But it becomes a bit
endless. I mean, like people were dying
around the world. Most people need meet
people that are dying. And so are we if
we're trying to be I think was in the
spirit of actually having people that
were directly facing um end of life and
and their companions. But I I think
again that's you know one could easily
argue to be um you know to be more um
more broader around that. But yes, the
way I create I wrote it up on there it
would be for people um who had a
connection with somebody who's using
this assignment.
>> Yeah. So I might on that one. I think my
feedback is is I would maybe I think
first of all it's really expansive and
cool that we're looking at not
necessarily the person who's dying but
people around him who are experiencing
that distress. So they may feel it
stronger than the person going through
it. Um but uh I I might suggest that the
person in the end of life not have to be
going through therapy. Sorry, they've
got like a bad ABBA song playing behind
me. that uh that maybe it not be based
or required on the person dying or end
of life that they be going through the
therapy that that end of life could
independently
exclusively apply to the person the
family member and I hear what you're
saying that could be a slippery slope of
you know who is it you're exactly
grieving for but I think you could put a
criteria there that it must be a direct
family member or someone that you were
directly responsible for being a
caretaker of
>> so that we are putting some sideboards
but I would suggest maybe not require
that the person going through it
themselves
>> because it doesn't cost the program any
more money to do that and have it be a
little more expansive. It just kind of
utilizes the law to allow a little bit
broader
>> broader coverage there for people going
through that. So anyway, that is my
feedback but fantastic job to all you
guys. Thank you so much.
>> All right. And next we've got Ian Dunn.
And Ian, you can unmute when you're
ready.
>> Yeah. I was actually going to go um
along with what he had just said. Um
that it not for the purposes I believe
for like the implementation part it is
good to have them and be a similar
experience. Um but for the actual
implementation of the program probably
including some sort of grief. Um that
way they can qualify equally under the
law without um
being like a plus one where they would
have to be with them. Um even if we do
end up saying like ideally right they're
with that person. Um
and then two alongside that the equity
fund also um it could be divided. My
concern with it being divided was that
um it could create the illusion of a
preference over a certain disorder if um
one fund runs out and there are others
available. um especially given that
there may be different rates of people
with um the disorders, therefore making
it harder to say um definitively let's
give X amount of dollars to this fund or
Y to this one. Um although I do like the
premise behind it. Anyway, those were my
two cents. Thank you.
>> All right. Um, and Chris Caldwell. Um, I
have enabled your mic and you can
unmute.
>> Hi all. Great to be here. Larry, I loved
what you said, especially about
reconsidering those exclusions. And I
couldn't help but think about um folks
approved for medical aid and dying. And
you know, there's yeah, usually some
talk about approving psilocybin
automatically if somebody gets approved
for medical aid and dying. And I just
wondered if you wanted to put that on um
you know in terms of exclusions.
But anyway, um kind of uh expanding on
what I heard Jeff say, you know, when
you had said for a progressive illness,
anybody with less than 3 years um
expected um you know, lifespan that you
you know, you don't have that three-year
sort of restriction because anybody um
you know, diagnosed with ALS or MS or
Parkinson's, you know, may uh um may
experience existential or physiological
distress. us right off the bat.
>> That's all I
>> Good points, Chris. Chris, appreciate
that. Good good points. And as I say,
these are just I'm really glad that
we're getting a discussion out about um
you know, about about all of them. I
mean, I think certainly, you know, we
want to be expansive. We, you know,
psilocybin, you know, may be helpful for
people having all different kinds of
grief. We're just trying to a little bit
try to figure out what is the uh
interpretation of um um of end of end of
life care. And um I I agree with you. I
mean I think there's also arguments that
that you may want people to be using the
psilocybin sooner like you know in other
words you don't want people to be like
getting a diagnosis of breast cancer and
the fact that you know it's not
metastatic being or that they don't have
access. So I think you're right there
there are certainly arguments to not
having those limits. um and or at least
changing the limits.
>> All right, let's see. Next, uh we've got
Gregory Evans, and you can unmute when
ready.
>> Um I'm going to run through a couple
notes
here. Um but something you just said um
may triggered something I hadn't really
thought about and the existential
distress of other forms of debilitating
or
um
disabilities like say somebody was in a
car accident lost their legs. I think
that is like a potential future use case
for um coping with that immediate um
understanding that like I I think it's a
very different thing to take psilocybin
for for end of life
um 3 years into a diagnosis versus like
holy [__] my whole life just
um man my language I apologize um but
yeah like the immediate uh reaction to
understanding that you will be dying. Um
the the notes that I had here is on the
intake data and intake requirements. I
think this is an excellent example of uh
how we should be working towards unique
um intake data and requirements for each
of the pathways. um PTSD substance use
are going to have different layers of
flexibility and complexity than than end
of life and you know so I think every
every column should kind of have its own
uh codified intake uh structure uh
potentially. So um on the family thing
uh companions of EOL participants
couple things I think this is a great
opportunity to um to perform co-f
facilitation and introduce a group
therapy model um where some of the other
modalities that we're exploring may not
have uh group therapy expression. uh
this could be an excellent way to work
with that. Um I think the multiple
pathways of I am supporting a person who
is going through dying and I want to
process my trauma around that versus um
I'm supporting somebody as a family
member and want to be present for their
their journey, their session and you
know like the bigger parts of that or I
want to do that journey with that
person. Um I think those are interesting
intersections of potential
administration
uh pathways. Lastly on the data
gathering uh for so for the the funds if
we did say we split it up like quarter
quarter quarter each like
each column gets its own chunk and that
is going to be
not that that the data that we could
gather from the fund distributions
correlating to their unique demographic
alignments
could be really really interesting. See
who from what zones of demographic um
identities are seeking assistance with
which type of therapy and that could
tell us a lot honestly. And then again
to uh I believe Dr. Steinborn said um
uh we should it said in the chat but
mentioning that the reallocation terms
should be defined as we if we do set
something like that. So as funds dwindle
we understand that we can petition to
have funds moved or be not specifically
gated to that therapy model. That is
all. Thank you.
All right. Uh let's see. And next we've
got uh Lita Fati. And you can unmute
when you're ready. Thank you so much.
What an amazing conversation. Um on the
topic of maid that Chris brought up. I
think that is such a great idea to have
that conversation with individuals who
are considering maid. um to have this
psilocybin assisted you know session um
to be a conversation and an option for
them um I think that's fantastic and the
way we handle maid in the state of New
Mexico is just one of the best
um processes that we have in the country
and so I want to highlight that as well
uh the role of our volunteers the role
of just it's it's a beautiful process
that we can also learn from when we're
implementing um psilocybin into end of
life. Um so great idea there. Um, one
thing that you brought up, Gregory, was
about, you know, loss of a limb. And I
recently read a study about phantom limb
pain and box therapy plus psilocybin and
how that phantom limb pain, which can be
so difficult to treat, almost
impossible. Um, this patient, you know,
it was a case study, but um, this
patient, you know, was treated through
box mirror and psilocybin use. So really
great applications and I know it's
outside of this scope but the other part
that
in the end of life realm I've seen being
used very effectively is the use of
micro doing. I know this can be a
discussion for later on, but I do want
us to not forget about the power of
micro doing and the shifts in perception
that micro doing provide for individuals
at the end of life. individuals who are
caring for uh end of life patients who
may not be able to take the time to do a
macro do session or they don't want to
participate in a macro do session or
they're on too many medications or they
have too many GI issues or and on and on
and on. I've seen micro doing have an
incredible
um
you know um really treatment and and
transformative
potential
um with with guidance as well and a lot
less complication almost no complication
like not almost I've never seen a
complication with micro dosing and yet I
do see the changes um and with families
too you know I recently We had an
interview with a um husband and wife and
the husband has brain cancer that is um
metastasized due to melanoma all
throughout his body including brain and
his you know very pleasantly confused
and the wife who has been married to him
for seven years is going through a very
difficult time um severe depression and
she's had depression throughout life so
treatment resistant depression session
and you know I I would have loved to be
able to send her somewhere or like be
able to guide her and I'm like hey
educate yourself. That's all I can do
right now. But um we really have a big
need in our community in this population
both for patients and um and family
members, caretakers. Thank you so much.
>> All right. Um, and next we've got Jamie
Beichy. And Jamie, I have allowed your
mic and you can unmute uh when you're
ready.
>> Thanks so much. I'm Jamie. Um, I am
spiritual health practitioner and I have
an affiliation with the Emory Center for
Psychedelics and Spirituality out of
Atlanta, but I'm here in um, Santa Fe. I
just had a few comments quickly. One is
about the inclusion of of loved ones.
Um, I would love to see loved ones
included in the preparation and
integration for
uh the, you know, the the person we
might call the patient or the or the
primary client. Um, regardless of
whether or not they might want to pursue
psychedelic support themselves. And then
as the as the care care diad or uh
practitioners really get to know those
folks perhaps they could identify who
would most benefit from from psilocybin
therapy. Not sure what that would look
like in terms of the um timeline of you
know the screenings and all of that but
it'd be great to center the loved ones
and include them either way would be the
ideal as as is uh the practice in
paliotative care
and hospice. And then I would also um
you know the tricky part with that might
be that you know if a person if the
loved one dies and then the caregiver
you know remains dealing with grief they
might move from anticipatory grief to
dealing with the actual loss. And so
maybe there's a need for some
flexibility there as well as including
people whose um you know loved ones are
are are in hospice or at the end of life
and maybe um don't want to receive
psilocybin therapy. So hopefully again
broad like everyone else is saying and
inclusive. And then secondly, I'm
wondering instead of the um this is just
a thought, but instead of um relying on
a time projection for a terminal
diagnosis, maybe like a a list of
qualifying diagnoses or something or or
certain kinds of um you know, diseases
and illnesses that are likely to
lead to the the person's death within a
three or four year period. because
really it's hard for I think it would be
difficult for practitioners to make that
kind of projection and also um you know
something like ALS for which there there
really is is no cure is a different kind
of an experience than maybe um something
that can be chronically managed over
many many years potentially. So those
are my thoughts.
>> Awesome. Thanks Jamie. Um, and next
we'll go to Ian Dunn, and you can unmute
when you're ready.
>> All right. Uh, thank you. So, I wanted
to address what, uh, Dr. Fatmi and
Gregory were talking about. Um, I know
at least in the patient qualification
and safety committee, we adopted
existentials distress um, with any
lifelimiting illness. So, if they did
lose a limb, if they had phantom limb
pain that was so bad, you know, it gave
them that existential distress um or
that kind of event, they would be able
to qualify under that. Um, but I did
want to also bring it back to the
exclusions for this program. So, I um
100% agree with uh Larry that the
exclusions need to be softer for end of
life care. when you get to end of life
care, um the
costbenefit analysis of different
medications changes. Um so we're not
really worried about substance abuse as
much. We're not really worried um about
hypertension or that kind of thing
because again that costbenefit analysis
has shifted. So I think it is important
that we um open up what if that is their
qualifying condition kind of open up
those restrictions and ease them out
because um they are meant for you know
people that
have
more to lose. um in terms of you know if
they get organ damage they may have
another 30 40 years to live with that
organ damage versus um maybe three years
but I will turn it over um thank you.
>> All right and Larry
>> um yeah first of all I love all the
comments and everything. We're
definitely going into uncharted
territory here. So, it's great to have
lots of different perspectives. And um I
just wanted to um mention um Jamie, what
you brought up I thought was was a great
point which is about when people are
having an end of life therapy, you know,
bringing in their their family members
or other things. And I just want to
mention we do have one other area on our
scopes that we really haven't addressed
which is kind of the whole care plan
which um gets into things like that
involving family involving spiritual
care. So I think that would be um that
would be a great discussion to have um
uh have in the future and be really
helpful I think for um for um input. I
know I think Jennifer's here from Red
Willow from hospice and stuff to to
share that share that information. um
you know as we move forward.
>> Thank you.
>> Awesome. Uh let's see. Next we've got uh
Joel Rosen. And Joel, I've enabled your
mic and you can unmute when you're
ready.
>> Hi there. Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Yes. Perfect. Amazing discussion. This
is so exciting and I I just love the
how this is expanding. It's when we
started this had very limited thoughts
about how this was going to play out. So
I just one thought and I agree with a
lot of the comments uh but I think as we
talk about and I I do a lot of medical
aid and dying. It's a big part of my
practice and I do a lot of ketamine um
in preparation for medical aid and
dying. And so I'm in this space a lot
and and one thing that I see and I I
love the idea of how we include the
family in in this process. I personally
have not had a situation where family
members have opted to do ketamine
although it's often discussed and and
offered but I think as and and maybe
with psilocybin uh people will be more
interested I don't really know but I
think especially with maid patients one
of the things I see that there's a
period of time once their loved one has
passed where things are quote unquote
quiet and then there's a fair amount of
and I stay in touch with families for
usually at least a year after their
loved ones dies.
I I there's there's kind of a time, I'm
going to say 6 to to 12 months where
kind of things kind of fall apart.
People start to really struggle. that
I'm kind of I guess I'm going to kind of
add maybe a thought about um even after
a loved one has died and whether they
did or do not do psilocybin before um
their loved one died maybe allowing them
I'm going to just say a year after a
loss and especially with medical aid
dying I think that's a very unique uh
subset of patients um but I would say
especially for families who have a loved
one who have died using medical aid and
dying given the opportunity to to uh get
treatment with psilocybin up to a year
after such an event cuz um it's just a
very very different uh it's a different
way of dying and and I think families
cope with it in a different way. So I'm
just putting that out there as a
thought. Thank you.
>> Awesome. Thanks Joel. Um let's see. Next
we've got Greg Evans and you can unmute
when you're ready.
>> Dr. Rosen, I think you took a lot of the
words right out of my mouth. Um, what I
was going to bring up is just the idea
that having a system which provides for
ongoing like year plus integration care
for EOL survivors could be incredibly
impactful. Um, and I know that this is
like kind of maybe pushing outside of
the scope of treating distress, but it's
the it it kind of speaks to the need
that like integration networks and uh
providers that offer care well well
after the day of treatment is incredibly
important for the efficacy of all of
these therapies. But like it's very
interesting to think about those who are
left behind
and how we can help those people as
well.
>> Awesome. Thanks, Greg. And uh back to
you, Larry.
>> The um I I didn't have any more
comments. It looks like Jennifer, you
look like it says you're on hold. Did
you have uh comments or questions?
Jennifer Johnson.
>> Um I'm not sure what the onh hold thing
is. Let me see
because that just grays out the whole
mic area. Um not sure what that's about.
If you're able to put something in the
chat, Jennifer, then you can do that.
But yeah, I'm I don't feel like I've
seen before, so I don't know what's
going on.
>> On hold in Teams means that someone has
stepped away.
>> Okay, cool.
>> Well, great. I think this has been a
great discussion. Um, you know, lots of
um and I think it's a discussion that
we're going to want to continue as we
start trying to put things into into
writing. um what I feel is like a really
um united on a on an expansive vision of
what's involved in end of life care and
we're describing it in different ways
whether it's not having arbitrary time
limits uh including family and I really
like the last few comments and we're I
know I focused a lot on um the idea of
integration care for people with PTSD
and other things but I think the idea of
um
of of the having ongoing care um for the
um for the the grieving family members
is important and um and if that can be
considered in as end of life care and
grief you know I think that's very very
relevant.
So, if we don't have any more comments,
um well, um we're talking about having
our next meeting July 10th, 1 to 3 PM.
Um the one of the focuses of that was
going to be to have a couple of people
that have been very involved in using
psychedelic therapy and studies other
ways for for decades. One of them is
confirmed as Mary Kosamano from John's
Hopkins. So, that will be one area. Um I
I think another area that's you know if
you look at our original scope um which
we're starting to touch on today is is
the issue of um you know plan of care um
and it came up um you know as Jamie was
mentioning you know making sure that
there's you know that there's
involvement and in family members that
that be a standard thing bringing in if
people want that you know spiritual care
having plans for um you know for um
survivors after the loss. So I I think
that may fall into what we call the the
plan of care, friend of life care. And
so just encourage everybody to start
thinking about that and figuring that'll
be discussed in one of our future
meetings.
So thanks everybody. Great meeting. Love
all the comments. I love the direction
we're we're moving in. Um uh July I
know. Yeah, summers get hard. I know. So
July 10th, uh, you know, 1 to 3 PM, um,
definitely have Mary Kosamano. I hope to
have another person there, um, as well.
And then, you know, I I see us as having
gone through a lot of these informative
meetings. So, I think as we're moving
into, you know, September or so, I
really hope that we can be all be
working together to, you know, put some
put some papers to words and, uh, share
share this with the advisory board, um,
you know, and the greater public. So,
thanks everybody. Have a great day.
>> Awesome. Thanks, Larry.